so I was wondering if we can speak
about life and
death those two
phenomenons and uh death being the
counterpart of life but first there's a
sutor and it's called Uh fragile or
perishable says because I will teach you
the fragile and the UNF Fragile the
perishable and the UN
perishable what is the fragile and what
is the UNF fragile
form is the fragile it's sensation
subsiding passing away is the UNF
fragile so feeling is the fragile
perception is the fragile intentions are
fragile Consciousness is fragile their
sensation subsiding passing away is UNF
fragile un
perishable that fact of their
that fact of their
change remains M so those things those
particular things
change in various ways they subject to
change but one thing that is not uh Up For
but one thing that is not uh Up For
Debate or subject to change is
that yeah yeah they're
ending so in terms of
like we have the phenomenon of life
and its counterpart so here's life
everything that I'm experiencing now the
the all if if I can say that yeah uh
myself included yeah everything
and the background to
that is
this change is this death you got to
understand death as that background of
death is is
implicit so because it's usually like
death is perceived to be something at
the end of the
life yeah like when when when that time
comes then death will arrive so to speak
but actually death is already
here through the fact that you were
manifested that you were born already
implies as we say say often like the
um the manifestation of a thing anything
any phenomenon big or small fire on it
doesn't matter manifestation of a
thing is its impermanence the fact that
it's manifested the fact that it came to
be it's incomprehensible to you to stop
that or prevent that it's just it's
inaccessible the the manifestation of
things the presentation of phenomena
it's it's just something that's
completely outside of your
scope so death kind of it's on obviously
it's on that level is just in this in a
general sense if you take a the
phenomenon of your life the all that
happens while you're alive well the
implication of that life is that it is
that it has come to be it's
manifested so its sensation is implicit
in its manifestation that's what the
Buddha said like those who
are um
unmindful they're as if dead already
like you don't have to wait to
die in order to be within death all you
need to do is uh exist within the Mara's
domain or within the domain of that
which implies death that's already as if
dead because death is there through that implication
because if you see so if you see
life uh you you will see its counterpart
existing in the
background it's implication it's
implication it's it's it cannot arise
without that implication of
death life what you mean cannot arise I
mean you know the fact that it is
manifested yeah it cannot be conceived
apart separate from yeah it cannot be
conceive without that implication in the
broadest sense of that of that word so
the point is it's like what think like
like a simil say somebody is living
within a waiting
trap the big trap is just waiting to
crush you you're completely unaware of
the Trap you're completely unaware of
the the thing hanging over your head but
you have absolutely well by being
completely unaware that it's a trap you
have absolutely no no notion of escape
and even if you were to even if somebody
tell you oh it's a trap like you you
don't even know where to begin like you
don't even recognize it you don't even
know that there is anything to be
escaped or how to be escaped that's
pretty much the existence of of uh of
anyone who is living within the central
domain with the wrong view I being
pja so they're as if dead already like
yes technically their life their birth
is still manifested there because
they're still existing but within the
domain of the inevitable trap inevitable
sensation of that and and you can see
there and then while they're in that
state by not having the Right View by
not being being sensory strain you know
like they they don't even know they
don't even have a notion of the escape
and as such they might as well be dead
already uh so there's the other if you if you
uh so there's the other if you if you
cultivate the context of death then you
cannot you cannot Delight in life you
you you'll turn away from life or uh as
it says in the Su UPA will be
established um or the counterpart will
be established but meaning the context
will be clear death in the background
implicit if you cultivate that well
there you go again on the basis so the
same simil if you if you get the right
View and you recognize the Trap as a
trap you recognize that whatever has the
nature of arising that's why it's
impermanent whatever has the nature to
manifest that is its impermanence you
recognize the extent of the
Trap so if you then contemplate the
existence of the implication of death in
everything in every INB breath in every
out breath as the sutas would say it's
implicit like that context we said it
before but you know it doesn't hurt to
to um repeat it the contemplation of
death in the sutas that's often talked
about when it says like a monk should
contemplate within an in breath within
an out breath he shouldn't like he
should contemplate death it doesn't mean
he's doing it on the level it just means
that his knowledge his um correct uh
concurrent attending to the implicit death of this
attending to the implicit death of this
life permeates even the most immediate
action of breathing so you contemplate
death on the level of in breath and out
breath not by watching sensations of in
breath and out Breath You contemplate it
by developing that background context of
the implication of that death so so
thoroughly that even breathing will
remain cannot remain unaffected by that
context yeah any even the the core of
life exactly sign of life exactly even
even the most heartbeat neutral kind of
um habitual action that you generally
take for granted so even even even that
will will be permeated by the
significance of the implication of death
and you do that not just for the sake of
you know contemplate death so hard to to
reach that point where you just kind of
Boom you just step outside of it and
you're free you contemplate it so that
there is a complete
dispassion towards anything regarding
life life and that's how you step
outside of it and that's how you're free
when there is no more passion towards
that well that removes you place
basically cancels you within that uh
implication of death so in other words
you disappear from the trap let's put it
that way because you have no
issue if if a random trap Falls if you
not in that trap like it's not it's not
your problem cannot be your problem
so it's only a problem when you are the
one who's going to be trapped or hit by
that
thing so it so obviously or ordinarily
people will everybody knows I'm going to
die but that thought stands for
something abstract in the future stands
for idea of death which is like a very
much as I
said uh misconceived notion of something
that will happen at the end whenever
that end is and so on in the future with
the time so uh disconnected from this
life yeah you don't wait for you don't
well like if you know if if you need to
wait for the actual
dying to contemplate death it's too late
no you contemplate it within life within
that which was born within that birth
within that manifestation but
it although people know that or that
what they already when they think it's
at the end of my life that at the end in
the future um even if you had to cultivate
future um even if you had to cultivate
that thought every day for example like
some stoics might have done not that
they did exactly this but maybe at the
end of their day they might think well I
might die tomorrow or you know death is
coming and so on
and and they might cultivate that
particular thought abstract thought
about death being in the
future not in the sense that we're
talking about but being somewhere
else at some other point yeah not
connected with yeah not connected with
it's like a different thing it is yeah
yeah they don't see
it in the heart of their own present
existence so you a person like that who
if they had to somehow find the effort
to do that every day have those abstract
Notions of death still might be a bit
more careful yeah yeah no it's better
than being completely like ignorant or
or or or or like um uh deluded in regard
to it of course like it's it's better to
not forget that you that you will die
even in that kind of abstract secondary
remote sense that usual kind of um idea
of death is for people um it's it's
better than nothing but but like when
the Buddha was describing the
contemplation of that that that leads to
like the quickest way of this passion
and arship it has to be taken very very
differently Much More acutely Much More
precisely and much more
profusely if you were thinking about
death as an AB abstract thing in the
future coming and your mind
coming and your mind
becomes more um grateful for the present
things of Life mhm your mind goes into
the direction of delighting in life
really appreciating all the moments and all the
appreciating all the moments and all the
things that can
happen uh I think that is a sign that
you're not connecting this correct you
know that's very nice well again take
the Sim of the
Trap see if you're contemplating
uh pretty much any contemplation yeah
life if it's done acutely uh death if
it's done
acutely um trap contemplation of a trap
acutely you recognize that oh it's not
something that will come
later it's right there now as I think it
it's hanging over my head would you then
spend time going around saying thank you
to other people within the same trap and
expressing your gratitude you might say
it in passing if it comes up while you
are being preoccupied with with how to
free myself from the impending thing
that's going to crash on my head in this
trap I'm so grateful for this F exactly
like so it's even when people
contemplate it in that sense you
described those people not everybody but
then that um death is is is um is still
kind of removed so it's like yes it's a
trap and everything but the fact that
you think you have time to Express
gratitude and and S things out and and
appr appreciate things you wouldn't
appreciate stuff if you aware of the
imminent danger of that
stuff so only when that imminence is
removed you can kind of okay let me deal
with this and then I'll deal with it
when it comes but it's like recognizing
the imminence the implicit aspect the
life is the Trap the life is the death
the death you know they cannot have it
otherwise impossible but it's like the
separation because people see see it
separately yes separ
because of the accumulated views so they
don't see it simultaneously as the
counterpart to life is is surrounded
it's it's it's shell and they don't see
it simultaneously because seeing things
simultaneously requires training Against
the Grain against the directionality of your
Grain against the directionality of your
senses of your mind of of of everything
you know so you can't do it accidentally
you can't accidentally stumble upon the
clear image and relationship between
life and that would result in immediate
dispassion you become an Arun but you
can through repetition and through kind
of digging up that way against the grain
of your senses against the grain of Life
against that flow of you know forward
movement so to speak that generally it's
how people people's lives uh go so it
takes that effort to swim against the
current and one of the obvious um ways
of doing that is
taking on the precepts celibacy sense
restraint and then the contemplation of
that that like death
however um a remote
delayed non- imminent might have been
it's going to start narrowing down
because you are uh not maintaining the
cover up of the imminence of death
through your actions of sensuality will
non-restrained
engagement and you're containing and
then you're going to start Discerning it
on the right
level so those who
are mindful of
death well that's it see not being
forgetful of that context is the
beginning of that right mindfulness
that's what would have said those who
are forgetful I those who are unmindful
they're as if dead already
already
and only those who are mindful have an
opportunity have the to yeah eventually
penetrate on that acute level and
understand and see that would then
result not as I said in some magical
mystical experience but in complete this passion
experience but in complete this passion
towards anything concerned with
life doesn't mean they Delight in death
either they just mean they contemplated
sufficiently enough to to cancel out
theight in life
life and that's enough for
Liberation so someone gets that uh
context of
death how do they remember it you know
how do you keep it going throughout the
day oh you you're going to be forgetting
it you'll be you'll be getting
distracted you you you you you you keep
yourself from drifting away too far from
it by uh policing and restraining your
own action
which are delighting which would be
exactly which would be countering that
context of death see if you're acting
out of sensuality you have to put life
first you have to put the pleasure of
life even even more first um and that's
already a serious perversion of that
actual order and whenever you pervert
the order you cover up what's
implicit in the right in that order so
by by delighting in life by perpetuating
proliferating Delight through acts of
sensuality acting out of ill will acting
out of hindrances regarding life and
things that come up within that life you
are uh covering up the implication of
death in
it and every time you cover it up the
view that death is something later gets
established more and
more and as what you also have to feel
like threat yeah yeah cuz it's an immediate
threat yeah yeah cuz it's an immediate
threat it's not you certainly would
initially uh that's why it's very
important if you want to go down the
down this route of contemplating death
and similar contexts you better have
your aggregate of virtue properly
established because otherwise the mind
is just going to start freaking out in
regard to everything because it when it
will realize that there is no shelter up
down above below behind forward anything
in any direction I go to seek shelter
for myself it's under death it's under
the rule of death it's death it is
implicit thus it's not safe so only
person they will not be overwhelmed by
that is the person who already contained
the Mind from spilling over too far in
this irrational attempts of seeking
seeking safety that would then result in
its own
derangement because in then in a way so
if you aggregate of virtue is developed
then it's even though death is that
threat to life it can feel as a threat
and everything but it will be contained
because you have contained that which is
under the threat of
death so although you still
have some horses in that race so to
speak in other words you're not
completely fully dispassionate toward
life you have con you have contained all
those UNH wholesome ways of making your
dependence on that trap even worse so
when you start recognizing the Trap and
that which would be destroyed by the
trap you might feel some intensity but
overall it's contained because your
actions have been purified
beforehand and then you can take it
further so a person would feel the
threat and freak out only if they
haven't contained that uh yeah they
might like again whatever that intensity
might at the time might feel like the
highest intensity cuz it's not like you
can be outside of that experience and
compare it you know like whatever it's
the the current pain it's the worst pain
in in in everyone's life whatever's Cent
worry it's the worst worst worry uh but
whether they're doing it rightly or not
they can see whether how close to the
them breaking the precept and acting out
they are or not like in hindsight when
they look back week ago when I started
contemplating death and so on yes it it
felt close it felt acute it felt scary
but I haven't done anything on account
of it and that will already bring
confidence because that's the measure
have you done anything on account of it
and how bad was it how bad did your mind
make you act yeah so in the face of that
felt intent that that threat because
like well I can think about death I'm
not afraid of death like many people say
when I think about death I'm not afraid
of death it's not the death they're
thinking about could yeah when you feel a threat
about could yeah when you feel a threat
of pain little bit what do you do yeah
well exactly sure sure that's like if a
if a person wants to contemplate start
contemplating death if they say feel
like their virtue is decent they've been
restraining guarding the sense doors
they're not breaking the precepts
they're not engaging with sensuality
they're celibate and so on and they want
to practice you know a bit of
a a sharper approach such which is death
contemplation uh you don't start by your
ideas of death you just pick up
something that's dear to you and imagine
it being taken away where that feeling
of of pain is that's what death is so
take it then further there and practice
this passion towards it but it's also
yes so fi finding that those signs of
death almost you know picking up that
that flavor of death you know seeing
iming exactly that's mean like so those
flavors are actually to be found in
things that you don't that somebody
might not necessarily associate with
death with their idea of death they're
finally not getting what you
want being paid with what you don't want
being separated from what you want all
these things basically da examples of
daa wherever there is daoka the
direction of Dua that's what death is so
contemplate things that would cause you
suffering and you are contemplating
death then you take it further and it's
like yeah so I would be afraid I would
be I would be affected I would suffer if
I lose the loved
ones oh imagine how much more then so
through that same dukka of contemplating
losing the loved ones imagine losing
also these senses on account of which
you have your loved ones well that's
going to feel even
worse
yes so have imagine those things
contemplate that but then pick up this
that the sign of death B feel it feel it
feel it but again counterpart only only only
it but again counterpart only only only
on the basis of of uh thoroughly
developed virtue because
otherwise I mean this is not something
that that the Buddha was teaching to
householders by householders meaning
people that are not celebrate people
that might occasionally take on virtue
and you know go to Monastery and keep
get pret for a week or
something like because this is not for
most people who love will not be able
who love life love things in life their
families their children
whatever getting the flavor of
death means turning away from and
forgetting about never thinking about it
again and just indulging more into life
love life even harder because just just
cover it up uh and if you had to give
such a person the threat of death while
they were still delighting so much in
that life well you get what the suas
describe when they heard a Buddha
describe nibana from their standpoint of
very much cherishing life possessions
and everything else they as sud describ
they fell on the ground beating their
breast pulling their hair and saying
like oh that will kill us that will
destroy us yeah it's like people in in
on death row in some of these in America
they don't they on death roow but they
they could be executed any day so
there's always this threat hanging over
the head yeah and they are not really
wanting to be there yeah they would
rather not distract themselves from that
which they go crazy you know yeah it's
like the worst kind of well yeah that's
what that's what Doki was writing about
the house of
dead in the prison from his experience
in the prison basically he he saw that
the worst punishment to give to a man
that you know a man I a householder that
loves life that that does not see the
problem in sensuality is to like have a
Perpetual possibility of
execution like there were people there
they were same that death row and they
might be killed tomorrow they might not
sometimes they were taken out to The
Gallows and then sent back and it's like
unbearable mentally and they all just
disintegrated and he was he was affected
by by witnessing that because as that
other s describes it's like um when the
man was talking to the Buddha you
brought it up recently when it said oh
you know like we love life um Family
sensuality household like just the idea
of renunciation feels like a precipice
feels like falling into the abyss just
the idea of renunciation it's like if
renunciation scares you that much well
imagine how much forceful renunciation
will scare you death yes when when
things are forcefully taken away from
you when you are when when basically
where where where your own mind does the
renunciation for you like like without
you wanting it when your senses just
fail so it's like you already get the
flavor through practicing renunciation
that's why it's just generally so scary
you say to people are you you got to be
celibate it's like like you you you put
on the greatest fear on them it's like
well forever like I will never
experience the pleasure of the senses
again it's like it's like
death from the point of view of those
whose minds are still very much imbued
with sensuality and do not see danger in
that trap but seeing it as danger no longer
trap but seeing it as danger no longer
delighting in life
which yeah so like you brought up the
example of of a person who say uh might
experience that flavor and then double
down in commitment to the life and
loving life and family and so on it's
like so
if somebody experien the flavor of death
gets a hint of it and they might they
recognize they're not able to like dwell
on it and contemplate it
rightly at least don't cover it up twice
as much as before so allow that that
that kind
of background hint of that doubt and
fear to stay there okay you don't have
to go fully towards it if you have not
prepared the basis of virtue sensory
strengths liy and so
but at least don't cover it
up don't completely cover it up because
they were they were PJ they were
philosophers they were religious people
they weren't so intoxicated yeah exactly
and they were not withdrawn from
sensuality and so on but they did have
the capacity through practice to not
completely cover that up and it did
shape their life more
wholesomely it's not ideal because they
still stay
pjan but I'm saying is if somebody who
also has access to the instruction of
the Dharma and then practices that
non-complete cover up of death well it
it would certainly bring you even closer
to the right View and then eventually
you'll realize you might realize that
that giving up
sensuality is not as scary as you
thought it was and you work up towards
it and and then and actually start
containing your mind on that level where
it
matters so if you do see it right death
rightly and you start renouncing
sensuality start renouncing the
world well no you got to startop but
yeah you might have that in the don't
cover it up and then start renouncing
yeah sure sure that can be like a wake
up call I'm going to die yeah and
there's no way I can escape so
to so how can you how can you
escape the implication of
manifestation when you yourself anything
you know about yourself any possession
any ownership is just another
manifestation inconceivable so a person
who's actually moved by
that thought
in uh and starts doing things rightly in
in accordance with it starts to
like let me stop being a bit careful let
me find an answer to this issue and then
starts to contemplate it more and
more and finds
himself uh you know virtuous
dispassionate towards
life then as atut says you know either
he fully dispassionate towards
lifea gets
established so it's not like he's in
this paranoid no fear no or disgust and
hates everything exactly that that might
you might you might have episodes of
that but again with the right
instruction which is abundant with the
sutas and so on you recognize okay no
it's about
the whole dwelling on on death and
recollecting it and not forgetting it is
just so to experience to develop the
complete dispassion towards anything
concerned with life just to that extent
not more not
less and when that dispassion is
established you recognize okay so now I
neither Delight in that life nor do I
Delight in death I certainly don't fear
it because I have nothing to lose
anymore whatever's here will have to not
be here yeah because it's here no for no
other reason but seeing life you seeing
it correctly that you will see well when
you you're basically contemplating in
each of their life counterpart death oh
yeah yeah of course you just and the
realization it's not mine this is never
was mine well exactly through this
passion because passion maintains the
ownership acting out of passion
maintains the ownership possession
consumption all these all these not this
phenomena it's just how you maintain the
ownership the ownership when you realize
that when you start contemplating and
establish the context that's that's uh
incompatible with the growth of passion
towards things the mind just can't go in
that direction because of the whole
framework of death that's being seen in
regard to it like you go and reach this
fruit to eat it easily you enjoy it well
then you suddenly recognize through
discernment that there is a massive actx
waiting to chop your hand each time you
reach for the fruit oh the significance
the joy of the fruit very much changes
it becomes actually dangerous so the
taste hasn't changed it all remain the
same it still tastes the same the
greatest fruit ever known to man but now
you see a an axe waiting to
fall and it's like oh it's not the same
thing anymore isn't it so the mind will
not go and just oh yeah yeah give me
that fruit let me reach for it because
it sees what's
implicit and you contemplate it long
enough it will stop being scary because
you recognize well there's nothing scary
about a ax hanging over a random fruit
it becomes scary when my hand is in
between the two or my
head so now when you recognize the
danger you don't have to well you have
to practice sensor strain because of the
habits but when that's been thoroughly
done you don't have to
then stop yourself from reaching just by
having that context means mind will not
be reaching that's why the the said one
whatever you frequently think and Ponder
that's what will become the inclination
of your mind you're frequently pondering
about the taste of the fruit and how
great it is and the texture well the
mind isn't losing its broader context
and it's becoming more obsessed and
focused on the aspect of the taste the
beauty the beauty exactly and but if you
frequently contemplate the hanging
ax well then the mind is is is is
inclining towards oh avoiding that
danger because it's factually
dangerous so then restraint becomes
effortless you don't need to restrain
yourself because you don't want to do it
in the first place